Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Records 5467
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Records
1919-1973
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen (BLF&E)
BLF&E Local 807
5467
4.61 cubic feet
4.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection consists of the records of Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, Local 807, located in Auburn, New York. Consists chiefly of correspondence regarding employee claims and grievances, the wage-rules movement, mergers, and routine business matters; also, routine administrative documents, forms, certificates and schedules, and financial records.
2298751
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 09, 2013
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, December 04, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen was founded on December 1, 1873 in Port Jervis, New York by Erie Railroad firemen in order to provide mutual support for railroad firemen. Their first convention was in 1874, at which they adopted their first constitution. The Brotherhood initially emphasized insurance, but by the late nineteenth century had branched out into labor-management relations.
In 1907, the organization changed its name to the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen [BLF& E], reflecting the changes in its membership as former firemen were promoted to engineers and permitting locomotive engineers to join its ranks. In 1969, the union merged with the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and the Switchmen's Union of North America to form the United Transportation Union [UTU].
Lodge 807 of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, now defunct, was located in Auburn, New York. It was composed of employees of the Lehigh Valley Railroad Company [LVRR] working on the Lehigh Valley, Auburn, Cortland, and Auburn-Ithaca branches. These employees were represented by Lodge 807 until its dissolution in 1966 at which point they were represented by Lodge 379, located in Sayre, Pennsylvania. After the merger of the railroad brotherhoods, they were represented by UTU Local 810. Finally, in the 1970s, the operating employees joined the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers [BLE], Division 380, Auburn-Cortland Division.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1919-1973
Bulk dates: 1925-1958
This collection consists of the records of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen [BLFE], Local 807, located in Auburn, New York. The members of this Lodge were employees on the Lehigh Valley Railroad [LVRR] on the Lehigh Valley, Auburn, Cortland, and Auburn-Ithaca branches. This collection, when examined along with Collection 5869, offers a mostly complete historical portrait of a BLFE Lodge and a glimpse into the day to day work of railroad employees in upstate new York during the first half of the 20th Century.
This collection contains the log books of Local 807's recording secretary, which contains the records of the Lodge's meetings, members, dues, and elections. The collection also contains the minutes of meetings for the General Grievance Committee of the Lehigh Valley Railroad, which offers a broader view of both the BLFE and the LVRR system. The records from the General Grievance Committee also contain the records of an on-going dispute between the Auburn and Cortland factions of the Local 807 firemen and enginemen regarding their seniority districts, work rosters, mileage equity, and rights to specific runs on branch lines. The two factions, each responsible for separate branch lines, had their rosters merged in 1932. This led to an ongoing conflict between the members of Local 807 for the remainder of its existence. As the LVRR was forced to abandon branch lines in the mid-20th Century, these disputes grew more contentious, finally culminating in having the International President decide on the matter (see box 6, folders 6 and 7). Extensive records of mileage worked by the various employees were kept by the local to argue their individual cases. The situation was further exacerbated by conflicts between the BLFE and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers [BLE], and who had the standing to represent the LVRR employees. As a result, there were multiple local chairmen, both de facto and official, who worked on behalf of their own factions. As a result, the correspondence files have a great deal of crossover between the LVRR General Grievance Committee and the various Lodge officials, who all kept separate correspondence files but were oftentimes writing to each other.
These correspondence files make up the bulk of this collection. Major correspondents include: William H. Sullivan and Louis Edelmayer (BLFE general chairmen, Lehigh Valley System); James R. Lathrop, Harry Glowacki, William Welhaf, and F.W. Fehr (local chairmen, Lodge 807); J.N. Haines, C.W. Wagner, and various officials of the Lehigh Valley Railroad; and the financial secretaries of Lodge 807. Subjects discussed include grievance cases, violations of the union shop agreement (1956), the abandonment of lines, discontinuance of passenger service, fringe benefits, vacation agreements, and internal union issues, including the Auburn and Cortland conflict. The correspondence files of the financial secretaries contain records of the expenses of running a BLFE Lodge. The monthly financial reports are also found in this collection as well as the annual filings with the IRS and the Railroad Retirement Board. The financial records also contain complete membership lists, information of insurance policies, and applications for membership.
Additional documents include various union organizers' forms, rosters for LVRR divisions, contracts and agreements between the BLFE and the LVRR, and publications of the BLFE.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5141: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5141 G: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Graphics 5141 MB: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Memorabilia 5176: Grand Lodge of the Ladies Society of the Former Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5467: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Records 5475: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen General Chairman, Boston and Maine Railroad Records 5611: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Honorary Register of Disabled 5646: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Additional Records 5869: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Additional Records 6176: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Additional Records
Railroads--Employees.; Railroads--Employees--New York (State)--Auburn.; Grievance procedures. Railroads. New York (State); Locomotive engineers; Locomotive firemen; Railroads--Employees; Labor Unions--Mergers--United States; Labor Unions--Consolidations--United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen.; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen. Local 807 (Auburn, N.Y.); Lehigh Valley Railroad; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers
2298751
- Recording Secretary's Record, Lodge 807, Auburn, NY, 1919-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Officer Roll, Minutes, and Member Lists
- Recording Secretary's Record, Lodge 807, Auburn, NY, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Recording Secretary's Record, Lodge 807, Auburn, NY, 1951-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- General Grievance Committee, LVRR, Minutes of Meetings, 1925-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  1925-1930, 1934, 1936-1940, 1943-1945, 1946, 1948, 1951
- General Grievance Committee Action on E&C and L&NY Branch Line dispute, 1925-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Regarding mileage disputes and employ of enginemen and firemen from the two branches, headquartered in Cortland and Auburn, New York.
- Correspondence re E&C and L&NY Branch Line dispute, 1927-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Conflict between Auburn and Cortland employees re mileage, seniority, and rostering.
- Auburn Mileage Reports, 1937-1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  In re disputes between Auburn and Cortland divisions; and between committees of enginemen and firemen. Reports are in regards to the merger of the Auburn and Cortland rosters in 1932 on the LVRR.
- Cortland Mileage Reports, 1938-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Cortland Branch Correspondence, Grievances, William Welhaf, Lodge 807, 1927-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Correspondence mostly in regards to the merger of the Auburn and Cortland rosters in 1932 on the LVRR and dispute between the two branches.
- Cortland Branch Correspondence, General, F.W. Fehr, committeeman, Lodge 807, 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Correspondence mostly in regards to the merger of the Auburn and Cortland rosters in 1932 on the LVRR and the dispute between the two branches
- Cortland Branch Correspondence, General, Nicolas Fiske, committeeman, Lodge 807, 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Includes series of letters between Sullivan, Lathrop, Wagner, and Fiske re a fireman (Ryan) who is in violation of the Union Shop Agreement.
- Seneca Falls Branch, Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Dispute regarding seniority districts and rosters of firemen
- Correspondence, J.N. Haines, LVRR General Manager, and Louis Edelmeyer, general chairman, BLFE, 1929-1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Docketed grievances; decisions; general bulletins for distribution
- Correspondence, J.N. Haines, LVRR General Manager, and Louis Edelmeyer, general chairman, BLFE, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Docketed grievances; decisions; general bulletins for distribution. (W. H. Sullivan takes over as BLFE General Chairman in October of 1945)
- Correspondence, Docketed Cases and Decisions, 1946-1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Between C.L. Wagner, chief of personnel LVRR, and W.H. Sullivan, general chairman, BLFE
- Correspondence, W.H. Sullivan, General Chairman BLFE, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Docketed cases, decisions, bulletins, personal correspondence
- Correspondence, W. H. Sullivan, General Chairman BLFE, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, W. H. Sullivan, General Chairman BLFE, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, W. H. Sullivan, General Chairman BLFE, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  January-June, 1955. Docketed cases, decisions, bulletins, personal correspondence
- Correspondence, W. H. Sullivan, General Chairman BLFE, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  July-December, 1955. Docketed cases, decisions, bulletins, personal correspondence
- Correspondence, W.H. Sullivan, general chairman BLFE, 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, General, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, General, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, General, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, General (1 of 2), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, General (2 of 2), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, General, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, General, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, General, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, General, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, General, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, General, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, General, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, General, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, General, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, General, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman Lodge 807, BLFE, 1946-1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  January-May, 1956
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  April-June, 1956
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  July-December, 1956
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  January-June, 1957
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  July-December, 1957
- Correspondence, James R. Lathrop, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Harry Glowacki, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1950-1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  July 1950-June1953
- Correspondence, Harry Glowacki, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  July-December1953
- Correspondence, Harry Glowacki, Local Chairman, Lodge 807, BLFE, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Correspondence re Track Abandonments On LVRR Auburn-Fair Haven Line, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  February-May, 1952. Includes newspaper clippings and ICC filings
- Correspondence re Track Abandonments On LVRR Auburn-Fair Haven Line, 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Including correspondence regarding the changes in Seniority Districts and mileage equity for firemen and enginemen from Auburn and Cortland and briefs filed by the Auburn Lodge to support their seniority rights over the Sayre Lodge.
- Proposed Changes, Auburn Branch, 1941-1950 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Zell C. Porter, Financial Secretary Lodge 807, 1943-1949 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Harry Welch, Financial Secretary Lodge 807, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Harry Glowacki, Financial Secretary Lodge 807, 1949-1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Financial Secretary, 1952-1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Forms: Applications, 1944-1949 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Approval of Application for Insurance Certificates; Acceptance of Application for Memberships; and Re-Admissions of Former Members
- Forms: Applications, 1949-1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Acceptance of Application for Memberships; and Re-Admissions of Former Members
- Forms: Monthly Financial Assessments, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Forms: Monthly Financial Reports, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Forms: Annual Financial Reports, 1945-1957 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Forms: Railroad Retirement Board, Number 8918, 1947-1954 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  Quarterly payroll forms; mailers and instructions; blank forms; promotional materials.
- Forms: Railroad Retirement Board, Number 8918, Quarterly Tax Forms, 1944-1956 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Forms: Insurance, 1954-1958 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Death benefits, insurance pay-outs, and applications
- Forms: Semi-Annual Report of the General Secretary and Treasurer, 1958-1961 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  1958, 1961
- Forms, blank (Box 8, Folder 10)
  Undated
- Correspondence re Health Insurance for BLFE members, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Local Organizer's Receipt books, Report book, and Travelling Cards book (Box 8, Folder 12)
  Blank books of tear-out forms. Undated.
- LVRR, Buffalo Division Rosters, 1948-1950 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- LVRR, Agreement with, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- LVRR, Proposed Insurance Pay, Rules, Regulations, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- LVRR, bulletins and rosters, 1948-1955 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- BLFE Correspondence regarding Strike on Canada Pacific Railway, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- BLFE Pamphlets, 1922-1963 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- BLFE Magazine, vol. 155, no.1, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- "Ergonomics: Human factors in work, machine control, and equipment design" by Robert S. Schwab, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Letter from UTU to LVRR, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  Letter from LVRR employees at Geneva, New York regarding track condition